<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable word and call to all those called ranters or libertines through-out the three nations, to come into the true faith and pure fear of the Lord ... written ... by John Chandler ...</title>
            <author>Chandler, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1928</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19405</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12605895</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12605895</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64257</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31658)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64257)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 347:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable word and call to all those called ranters or libertines through-out the three nations, to come into the true faith and pure fear of the Lord ... written ... by John Chandler ...</title>
                  <author>Chandler, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conversion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64257:1"/>
            <p>A SEASONABLE WORD AND CALL To all thoſe called Ranters or Libertines THROUGH-OUT The three Nations, to come into the true Faith and pure Fear of the Lord, in this his Day of grace and viſitation; by turning into the Light of Chriſt, or witneſſe of God in their conſciences: from which they have ſwerved, and againſt which they have tranſgreſſed. Written in tender Love to their Souls, By <hi>John Chandler,</hi> Who hath been taken in the ſame ſnare; but by great Judgment redeemed out of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:64257:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64257:2"/>
            <p>TO all you who are or may be called <hi>Ranters,</hi> or <hi>Libertines,</hi> either for your looſe practiſes or principles (which ye eſteem to be good, pure, and without deceit); This is a word of knowledge or experience, from one who hath obtained mercy from the Lord, in turning to him that ſmote him: and, whether you hear or forbear, know and remember, that in a day of Grace, and an acceptable time, (wherein the Lord is gathering all ſorts of wanderers and ſtragglers into his fold), Ye have been put in mind, and warned to return; Even you I mean (in the firſt place), who formerly have had convictions of; &amp; trouble &amp; ſorrow for, ſin againſt the Lord; and after that, ſome inlets and openings of peace and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, and taſts of the good Word of God within you, and of the pure powers of the world to come, even of an endleſſe life with, and in, God, the Father of Spirits, whom ye then believed to be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great reward to all that walked before him in uprightneſſe, and with a perfect heart; as he declared to <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithfull, who ſaw Chriſt's day and rejoyced therein: Which melted your hearts, and made them tender; and you conſcious of thinking, ſpeaking, or doing, vainly, idly, or unjuſtly. Now, know this (all ſuch) that in the pure and unfeigned love of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (which dwelt in the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi>) do I write unto you, who truly and ſweetly ſaid to the Brethren, <hi>If any among you ſhall wander from the truth, and any one ſhall convert (or turn) him; let him know, that he which hath turned a Sinner from the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of his life, doth ſave a Soul from death, and cover a multitude of ſins:</hi> So it appears, there were thoſe in his daies who wandred from the truth, and ſo fell into errour of their life, as ye have done, which brought their ſouls into death, and danger of eternall death, which they could not ſee at the preſent, or (at leaſt) were unſenſible there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by reaſon of their wandring minds and hearts, which brought a Vail over the Underſtanding, or ſtupified the Conſcience; whereby it is no wonder, if ſuch then, and you now, did and do call Evill
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64257:3"/>Good, and Good Evill; put Darkneſſe for Light, and Light for Darkneſſe; bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter; Bondage for Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and true Liberty for Bondage; promiſing others Liberty, when they and you were and are both the Servants of Corruption; the cauſe of all which, hath been (I teſtify) the going from, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting that which firſt convinced and troubled for the Sin and Evil, whereby that conviction and trouble was thought to be raiſed up in the mind and conſcience, by miſapprehenſion or imagination onely, and not from a true thing or principle which was the true Light (that enlightneth every man that comes into the World) which could not lye, diſſemble, or flatter, but ſhewed Sin &amp; Evill to be ſo, becauſe they were ſo really; &amp; therefore troubled, &amp; vexed, &amp; terrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſinful Soul: So, by you called <hi>Ranters</hi> or <hi>Libertines,</hi> when ye grew into a carnall freedom, the Maſter of the Houſe was called <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elzebub,</hi> to wit, the pure, holy, juſt, and righteous Principle of God, taken by you but for a Fancy; whereby all that was truly good in you ſoon went to wrack, for hereby ſhipwrack was made of Faith and a good Conſcience: of Faith, becauſe there is nothing that doth or can diſcover to a Man or Woman's Soul, the true Object of Faith, but the true Light within, (which firſt reproveth, and then giveth the knowledge to the penitent and obedient) which Object of Faith or Belief is Chriſt; either, as the living Hope, Gain, and eternall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to thoſe that love him, keep his Commandments, and waite for him (as the Saints formerly witneſſed him); for, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, He that cometh to God muſt believe that he is, and that he is a Rewarder of thoſe that diligently ſeek him: or, as an eternal Judge, and Miniſter of the Father's juſtice, wrath, and vengeance to all that follow and obey him not, but their own Wills and Luſts, according as it is written; Tribulation and anguiſh upon every Soul that doth evil both to the Jew and Greek. So that ye, miſcalling the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in you for ſin, as aforeſaid, ſoon fell from this belief of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Reward and Puniſhment, looking upon man (as to his own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſelf) to dye and be but as the Beaſt that periſheth, (although, in the courſe of one Generation ſucceeding another, ye framed up a Unity and Salvation in your erring minds); whereby, even as a Ship that hath loſt his Anchor runs at randome in the Sea, ſo ye having loſt the Anchor of your Souls were let looſe to think Sin and Evil to be no ſuch thing, and ſome of you to commit all iniquity with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64257:3"/>For the ſtrong conſolation in the light by the Spirit, and hope, which the Saints have (which hope entreth within the Vail, even into the Glory that was with the Father, before the World, or ſucceeding Generations began) is the Soul's Anchor; as it was of Chriſt's the Elder Brother: Who for the joy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſſe and deſpiſed the ſhame, and is ſet down at the right hand of God: And the ſame that led you, not to believe this particular and eternal Reward, led you alſo to deny the eternal Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; when as Chriſt, who was the true Light, and meant as he ſpake without diſſimulation or equivocation, ſaith, <hi>If thy right hand or eye offend thee, cut it off or pluck it out, and caſt it from thee; for it is better to enter into life maimed, than having two hands or eyes to be caſt into Hell, where their Worm dieth not, nor their fire never goeth out.</hi> To which truth the Holy men of God in the Scriptures plentifully wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as knowing the terrour of the Lord, they perſwading men; for the Lord God is known by the Judgment which he executeth on the wicked, as well as by the Reward (which is himſelf) that he beſtoweth on the righteous: but ye being erred from the right Spirit (which <hi>David,</hi> after a fall, deſired might be renewed within him) in your own phanſies and imaginations, (Satan having transformed himſelf into an Angel of light within you) have put ſecret meanings and interpretations upon the Scriptures, as though Chriſt and the holy men of God did not really mean, as they ſpake, of theſe and divers other things (which I ſhall not now name parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly) but according as ye would have them to be underſtood: whereby Chriſt, the true light, and thoſe that were enlightned, and enlivened &amp; ſanctified by him, were by ſome of you accounted even ſuch as your ſelves, who live in divers luſts; ſo far hath the deceit entred into you: But ye ſhall know, in the day of the Lord's righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judgment, as I have truly known, by turning to that which judged aright and made manifeſt Sin to be exceeding ſinfull, that Chriſt, and the former Saints, and holy men and women, were ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in their thoughts, words, and deeds, haring no mental reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in what they ſpake; and that they lived according as their words hold forth, being wiſe as Serpents, (yet not in the Serpent's wiſdom,) and harmleſſe as Doves, yea, fleeing from all ſin and wickedneſſe as from a Serpent. And now I will ſay, How are the hidden things of <hi>Es;au</hi> ſearched out by the light, which is the Candle of the Lord,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64257:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>even of prophane <hi>Eſau,</hi> who for a morſel of meat ſold his birth-right? And let me (in God's wiſdom and fear) reaſon with you a little; Are not ſome of you prophane <hi>Eſaus?</hi> who, for a few momentary pleaſures and unſatisfying Luſts, have quite parted with, and for ever bid Adieu to, the ſenſe and feeling of that which ye once counted better then life it ſelf; to wit, a broken heart and contrite ſpirit, and godly ſorrow for ſin, which things wrought you to ſome Repentance, whereof ye had never juſt cauſe to repent: As alſo comfort and peace in your Spirits, as your minds were kept in that which was pure, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the Lord, and being afraid to offend him: Such a ſtep in the truth, no doubt, ſome of you have made; but now your hearts are as hard as an Adamant, ſo that ye find no more place for Repentance than <hi>Eſau</hi> did, nay, not going ſo far as he; for he ſought the Bleſſing with tears, (though he obtained it not, being ſtill prophane): but ye deſire not to returne, in any outward ſhew, yea, perhaps will laugh and ſcoff at any that ſhall exhort you thereunto. Had it not been good for ſuch, if they had never been born? And are you not all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ones, from the greateſt to the leaſt? that have left your firſt love to ſimplicity, and ſincerity, purity, holineſſe, ſobriety, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and other the good fruits of the Spirit, and think your ſelvs to have attained the higher perfection, the more freely ye can act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to theſe, without check or controul in your ſelvs, which ye count but the working of the Fancy; over which to get victory, that it ſhould not at all trouble you, ye count your perfection, redemption, juſtification, ſanctification, and ſalvation: So ye quench the Light, which is God's faithful witneſſe within you, (that in love often pleads with you for a return, &amp; kill the Juſt one, &amp; ſtop the cry of the innocent, &amp; trample upon the holy Seed that ſhould bruiſe the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent's head, who is head in you; &amp; call it your perfection &amp; redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; would (if it were poſſible) ſet God at variance againſt himſelf, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting that to be God's arme and power in you, which ſlayeth his reproving witneſſe, which is his good Spirit; which Spirit (know ye) ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with you for good: Therefore I charge you by the Lord, to bethink your ſelves (ye that are not paſt feeling) of your former eſtates when ye were conſcientious and tender, for it was much better then with you than now; and commune with your own hearts, by turning in to the witneſſe of God, that calls for purity and holineſſe in thought, word, and deed, for ſobriety and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64257:4"/>temperance and chaſtity, and all godlineſſe, and honeſty: and that while ye have time, leſt your conſciences be quite ſeared, and the Lord God ſware in his wrath, Ye ſhall never enter into his pure and everlaſting Reſt; for this is God's very and true day, (not an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary one, which ye have conceited, for ſome years paſt, to your ſelvs) and ſo no time to dally with the wicked and back ſlider; for, Woe (ſaith the Lord God) to him, that in the land and time of upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, will deal unjuſtly, and will not behold the majeſty of the Lord. And if any of you have, or ſhall have, ſtirrings and thoughts raiſed up in you of waiting upon God's witneſſe, and any true deſires be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, to know by the light within you (which makes manifeſt all things) wherein ye have erred and done amiſſe, I charge you flee it not, though it begin to bring ſome terrour and ſhame upon the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal part; for as ye have made the pure ſeed to ſuffer by your ſin and deceit, ſo you muſt expect to ſuffer by the Seed, when he comes to bruiſe the Serpents head, to whom ye have been joyned; and accept of the puniſhment of your iniquity, and ſay, It is all far leſſe than we have deſerved: and let your uncircumciſed hearts be humbled, and wait low and humbly to know the Lord's mind, and be willing to forſake all evill, and cleave unto, and do, all good that the Lord by his Light ſhall lay open before you, (who will bring Judgment to the line, and Equity to the plummet) and be willing to come into Unity with the Holy men of God, and Chriſt's words in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which teſtify againſt all the fruits of the fleſh, let them be done under never ſo fair a pretence of liberty; and above all things deſire ſincerity and uprightneſſe of heart, (for ſo it was with me at my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, and this was the word in me, His countenance ſhall behold the upright) and then will the Lord have compaſſion, and by degrees heal your land, I mean, your poor Souls, and ye ſhall ſee Faith in the truths of God, and a good conſcience, and the pure fear of the Lord, grow and ſpring up together in you; for 'tis Faith that purifies the heart: But if you <hi>flee in Winter,</hi> and will not bear the Judgment till the indignation be over-paſt, or will be aſhamed to be aſhamed of your evill wayes, and ſo let deceit prevail over the pure, and make up a healing to your ſelvs by quenching the witneſſe, ye ſhall receive the fruit of your own doings, even to lye down in perpetuall forrow in the end.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:64257:5"/>
            <p>But I hear ſome of you asking, What is Sin and Evill? Do ever any of you find any of the Holy men of God, from one end of the Scriptures to the other, to have asked ſuch a Queſtion? Nay. For they believed the Lord's witneſſe, which he had placed in them, without their own reaſonings, and diſputings; as finding twins in their womb, two Seeds oppoſite each to other, which brought forth contrary fruit; and by the Holy Seed, which is the true Light, they ſaw the good Tree, and the corrupt Tree; the good fruit, and the corrupt fruit: for the Light reproved them for evill and corrupt motions, and all words and actions proceeding there-from; but it juſtified them, and gave them peace in pure and holy motions, and all words and actions iſſuing from thence, which were ſeen to be of its own begetting: <hi>David</hi> witneſſed theſe two States; Saith he, <hi>Thou hast ſet my ſins in order before me;</hi> Mark, He believed God's witneſſe without diſputings; the Lord had ſet them before him, he therefore believed they were ſins, or that which was againſt the Lord, which his pure eye had a controverſy with: Now, the Lord doth not ſet a thing, that is not, before us, but that which is. Again, he ſaith, <hi>Oh Lord I am thy Servant, I am thy Servant, the Son of thy Hand maid, thou hast looſed my bonds;</hi> There he felt God's acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Juſtification, not in giving him a liberty to do what he liſt without controul, but in enlarging his heart to run the waies of his commandments, in which he was accepted, even in that which enlarged his heart ſo to do: For (ſaith he) in another place, <hi>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed, when I have reſpect unto all thy Commandments.</hi> Conſider alſo, that they were the wicked and ungodly who did ſay, <hi>Tuſh, our Tongues are our own, we will ſpeak, Who ſhall controul us?</hi> As if they had asked in deriſion, <hi>What is Sin or Evill?</hi> Not becauſe there was not ſuch thing in reality, (but onely according to mens ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion); but becauſe the Serpent had got ſuch a head in them, that they ſcarce felt a Controuler when they ſo ſpake. But if you will be to learn what Sin is, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>John</hi> in the courſe of their miniſtry (but not in anſwering ſuch a Queſtion propoſed to them by the Saints) do experimentally declare. The one ſaith, <hi>I had not known ſin but by the Law;</hi> Mark, the Law written in the heart by the finger of God (of which the two Tables of ſtone were a declaration) made <hi>Paul</hi> to know ſin to be Sin: Now, God's Law in the heart is Light, as <hi>David</hi> long ago witneſſed; and Chriſt is the true Light that Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64257:5"/>every man: Now, Chriſt was he which ſpake to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> (from whom <hi>Moſes</hi> received the Law, to declare it to the People,) as <hi>Stephen</hi> (when he was full of the Holy Spirit) teſtified: So then Chriſt, the Light, is the Law-giver, whereby Sin comes to be known; now, if he hath enlightned every man, and he be the true Light, then he ſheweth a truth to every man, which is, that he hath tranſgreſſed his Law or Light, by dark motions, words, and actions, ariſing from a contrary ground; and ſo ſin is not a ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or fained thing in any man whatſoever, becauſe ſin is known by a Law, which Law is Light, which Light is in every man, which Light is true, and diſcovereth nothing but a reall thing in every one: The other ſaith, Sin is the tranſgreſſion of the Law; He knew the Law in his heart, or the righteous principle of God, which he had been a Tranſgreſſour againſt: He doth not ſay, Sin is nothing but an appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion that there is ſuch a thing, but that ſin is a reall tranſgreſſion of a reall Law, or Principle of God. Again, <hi>John</hi> ſaith, all Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is ſin: There is Unrighteouſneſſe, and that of ſundry ſorts, both toward God and man, and all this Unrighteouſneſſe is ſin. Now, (ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> by the Spirit of truth), In every Nation, he that feareth God, and worketh righteouſneſſe, is accepted of him; But (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) all they that had pleaſure in Unrighteouſneſſe ſhould be damned: Here are contrary works really ſo, and they have contrary effects; for the wrath of God is revealed from Heaven againſt all Unrighteouſneſſe, with all which Unrighteouſneſſe the Gentiles were and are filled; to wit, with fornications, wickedneſſe, covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, envy, murther; Covenant-breakers, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, implacable, unmerciful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Who, (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) knowing the Judgment of God, that they which commit ſuch things are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of death, not onely do the ſame, but have pleaſure in them that do them. Here he witneſſeth, and we ſee and know it ſo to be; that they were filled with all Unrighteouſneſſe, and that the things mentioned were reall Unrighteouſneſſe; to prove which, none need go any farther than their own conſciences, wherein they knew and felt, by the true Light, the Committers of ſuch things to be worthy of death, (even eternal death, or ſeparation from the life and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God;) even as a Labourer is worthy of his hire; which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be an imaginary but a real thing.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64257:6"/>
            <p>But ye will ſay to me, The Patriarchs, Prophets, and Apoſtler; ſpake according to the ſeveral diſpenſations or miniſtrations they were under: The Jews before Chriſt were under a Vail; and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles (after the renting of the Vail of the Temple) though they ſaw clearer than they, yet not ſo clearly as we ſee now in this laſt and higheſt diſpenſation.</p>
            <p>The Vail that was over the Jews hearts conſiſted in this, that their Church-Miniſtry and Ordinances being according to the fleſh, letter, and written in Tables of ſtone, they felt not, for the generality of them, the Spirit and finger of the living God, writing his Law in the fleſhy Tables of their hearts, according to his new Covenant: Their Church were Jews outward; their Prieſts, Miniſters of the Letter, which left their Souls in death; who had need both to offer up Sacrifice for their own ſins as for the ſins of the People; and ſo the Law outward made nothing perfect, but it was the Miniſtration of condemnation to them, for want of quickning life from Chriſt to eaſe them, who is the Miniſter of the Spirit, and of Righteouſneſſe and Peace; at which Corner-ſtone they ſtumbled, becauſe of the old and long Vail that had been upon their hearts; which Vail, to this day, when <hi>Moſes</hi> is read in their Synagogues, abideth on them; who, when hey ſhall turn to the Lord, the Vail (which is a falſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of being accepted in their carnal Services, Performances, and Ordinances, from a literal rule, without a feeling of the life of Chriſt, in whom all Sacrifices ſhould be offered up) ſhall be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and then ſhall they feel a miniſtration of Righteouſneſſe in the Spirit, in reſpect whereof, their other miniſtration had no Glory. But what is all this (ô ye Libertines) to your purpoſe? for they were not, nor are, vailed in ſeeing ſin, (which the true Light that lightneth every man, reproveth to be ſin); for that is not from darkneſſe of Underſtanding, but from light ſet up there, without which they could not ſee it at all: Yea, this was that which miniſtred condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto them all, both the righteous and unrighteous, ſo far as ſin was ſtanding; and they could not, nor ought not, otherwiſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, becauſe elſe they ſhould, as you do, have believed againſt God's witneſſe in them, which is to make him a Lyar, an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble preſumption. As for the Apoſtles and Saints, both Jews and Gentiles, who had the Vail rent, and lived in the diſpenſation or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64257:6"/>of the Spirit and of righteouſneſſe, which exceeded in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that of condemnation (which was and is alſo glorious in its time and ſeaſon), Ye <hi>Libertines</hi> know nor, nor cannot know (while ye are as ye are) in what a high and ſweet ſtate they lived: But ye ſpeak proud and ſwelling words of vanity of things ye know not, nor live in; and would be at the top of the Ladder before ye are come to the foot, even to know Judgment upon the tranſgreſſour in you. Ye are not ignorant that the Apoſtles and Saints believed perfection, preſſed after it, and might obtain it; But that it was ſuch a perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which ye dream of, I utterly deny; for it was a deſtroying of all the Devir's works, and a plucking up of all the evill Plants which the heavenly Father had not planted, by Chriſt the pure power of God, who was manifeſted in the fleſh to that end. And know ye (Oh ye haughty and conceited ones) there is never any other new diſpenſation, different from this, to be brought forth in the World; but that the Glory of the Church in theſe laſt times is to be wrought out by the pure and powerfull appearance of the Lord God, in this very way of purifying and refining his People; for through Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is <hi>Zion</hi> to be redeemed, and her Converts with Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for Sin &amp; Unrighteouſneſs ſtaines &amp; marrs the beauty of any People or Perſon, making them to become droſſe, an ill ſavour, and a ſmoak in the noſtrils of God, and a fire that burneth all the day: Wherefore, that every thing which offendeth the pure eyes of his Glory may be gathered out of his Kingdom, will he purge his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by the Spirit of Judgment and burning; and, by fire, and by Sword, plead with all fleſh; and the ſlain of the Lord ſhall be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and thoſe (be they who they will, or have what high conceits they can of their own ſecurity) that will not fall upon his Corner ſtone, Chriſt, the true Light, that leads to the Life, that he may be broken, and humbled, and melted, by him, into godly ſorrow for ſin, and a ſorſaking thereof in thought, word, and work; this ſtone ſhall fall on him with a heavy hand at laſt, and grinde him to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: So, when ſuch a one is by the Judge delivered to the Officer, and then by him caſt into priſon, he ſhall never come forth out of thoſe chaines of darkneſſe, and that Dungeon of torment that the Almighty hath prepared for all the wicked, till he hath payed the laſt mite. Now, Let me ask you <hi>Libertines</hi> (that ſore ſo high in your talk of this laſt diſpenſation of God to his People) one Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64257:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>What do you think of the new <hi>Jeruſalom</hi> which is from above the holy City of our God? Is ſhe not the Mother of all the Saints? Is ſhe not the Bride, the Lamb's wife? and muſt ſhe not then be like the Spotleſſe Lamb her Husband? and doth not <hi>John</hi> in the Spirit teſtifie that there ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing that defileth, neither whatſoever worketh abomination, or maketh a lye, but onely they which are written in the Lamb's Book of Life, which muſt needs be none but thoſe that are free from all defilements; for, ſaith he, The fearful and unbelieving, and the abominable, and Murtherers, and Whoremongers, and Sorcerers, and Idolaters, and all Lyars ſhall their part in the lake which burneth with fire and Brimſtone; which is the ſecond death: Now what think you? Doth the Spirit in <hi>John</hi> mean as it ſpeaketh or not? Or did <hi>John</hi> mean as he ſpake? Do you think the mind of God in theſe words were to this purpoſe, that a man might do that which is counted Whoredome or Adultery, or Lying, or Drunkenneſſe, or Swearing and Curſing, or bowing to any Idol, or bewitch Peoples Souls or Bodies by Sorceries, or murther ones Neighbour, Brother, or Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; or do any other ſuch thing which is declared evil in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Truth; and yet, if he count it pure to him, and he ſee no evil therein, he may do it, and yet enter the holy City. Search with the light (if ye are not quite paſt all honeſty, tenderneſſe, and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) and ſee whether that doth or can give ſuch an interpretation thereof, or whether any thing but man's fleſhly and corrupted Will, and blinded Judgment can do ſo. But (Lord) how have ſome ſo darkned the pure eye, that ſhould ſee things as they are in truth and ſimplicity, by often tranſgreſſing againſt the Light that now they even (as deſperate) do not deſire to have the blind eye opened! But, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of glory, I beſeech thee for thy Seed's ſake, whom thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to gather from the remoteſt parts of the Earth, to ſhew thy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Arm in the ranſoming of them out of the hands of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Enemy, who hath beguiled theſe People, as he beguiled <hi>Eve,</hi> by drawing them to eat the forbidden Fruit, whereby they muſt needs know evil as well as good, whatever they may affirme (yet far from being as gods, but caſt out of Paradiſe) that ſo thy ranſomed ones may come (after Judgment known) wich ſongs to <hi>Sion,</hi> praiſing and magnifying thy holy name (as I have done and do) for thy infinite goodneſs and mercy never to be forgotten.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64257:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But ye make other Objections, as, Where there is no Law, there is no Tranſgreſſion; and, To the pure, all things are pure; and It's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> that the Lord will lead his People by a way that they knew not; and He will make Darkneſſe Light before them, and crooked things ſtraight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo, <hi>Solomon</hi> hath ſome expreſſions tending to confirme our Judgment; yea, and Chriſt himſelf ſaith, If the eye be ſingle, the whole body is full of Light; but if the eye be dark, the whole body is full of darkneſſe: ſo that all things are but as they are looked upon, and ſo is ſin and evil.</p>
            <p>Where there is no Law, there is no Tranſgreſſion, that's certain: but where is the man (as he is in the Fall) throughout the World that hath no Law placed within him, ſince the Law is light, and Chriſt the true light hath enlightned every man: So then there is real Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in every man, whiles in the Fall, for there is a Law left in him to ſhew it: now when as a man comes into the Law of the new Creature, or of the ſpirit of Life which is in Chriſt Jeſus, ſo as naturally to refrain from all ſin, and to do the will of God, the Law is no longer his reprover; and ſo where there is no Law, there is no Tranſgreſſion, and on the contrary: yet ſuch a one is not without Law to God, but under the Law to Chriſt; Let him that heareth under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. Likewiſe all things are pure to the pure: But that which is impurity it ſelf in the Root, as Pride, Envy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and thoſe words and actions which can flow from nothing elſe but that impurity, cannot be pure to the pure in heart, becauſe He cannot but hate all ſuch things: Now <hi>Paul</hi>'s words are exceedingly abuſed by unclean ſpirits; for he ſpeaketh of the things of this life, as Food, Rayment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (which are pure to one whole conſcience is not defiled with ſin) and they apply them to all thoughts, actions, and words which <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf often declares againſt in all. Tell me alſo (Oh ye Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines) is not willful murder ſomething? and Sodomy ſomething? and Men with Men ſomething, and Women with Women commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting filthyneſſe ſomething? and Man to engender with a Beaſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? and for a Witch out of malice, without juſt cauſe given, to do miſchief upon the Bodies of Men, or the innocent Beaſt, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? or to curſe ones Maker, ſomething? And dare any of you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64257:8"/>ſay theſe things are pure to the pure? do any of theſe, bear any face or reſemblance of or with purity? I believe very few of you would have the face to affirme it: Now if there be ſomething in you that riſeth up againſt theſe things, why ſhould it not alſo againſt other things which are declared by the Holy Men of God to be the fruits of the fleſh? and how, if but one thing be judged filthy in it ſelf, can all things in your ſenſe be pure to the pure? That place in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> is a Propheſie of Goſpel Times: the Jews had been long (before thoſe times came) led by the Letter of the Law, but then the Lord ſaid, He would lead them by a way they knew not, even by the teachings of His Spirit: they had before walked in darkneſſe, but now darkneſſe ſhould be made light before them, not (as a great Ranter once ſaid) that darkneſſe and its works ſhould be then accounted by them (that were taught of God) for light, and truly ſo; for that is impoſſible they being of a direct contrary nature: Now darkneſſe is truly ſaid to be turned into light, when the light and its works do expell the darkneſſe and its works, becauſe then theſe are not at all in being: as the darkneſs of the night, and works proper to the night, are not in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the day time; ſo night is turned to day. So <hi>John</hi> came to prepare a People for the Lord, even Chriſt, when the crooked perverſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was deſtroyed, and made a right and good nature, and the rough nature deſtroyed, and made a mild nature, that all fleſh might ſee the Salvation of God. As for <hi>Solomon</hi>'s expreſſions in ſome things; take heed of ſtumbling and falling at a wiſe man's words: He was once Captivated by Luſt, and Idolatry, and Pride; but conſider him in all his Rayment or dreſſe of Wiſdome and Knowledge as he was <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> a greater than <hi>Solomon</hi> is here, even Chriſt the true light of men, who ſaid, If thy eye be ſingle, thy whole body is full of light: The ſingle eye is, when a man looks ſingly to the Lord in all his thoughts, words, and actions, keeping the watch, that his mind run not out after other Lovers, ſo long is the Body full of Light, for the Light ſhineth out of the Darkneſſe therein; but if the eye be dark, if he looks or runs after any thing in his thoughts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beſides the Lord alone, there is the double-minded man, whoſe heart is to be purified; for darkneſſe fills his Temple, that he knoweth not what he doth in ſo doing. So that the ſingle eye is not to look on ſin to be no ſin (for that is to ſee a lye) but to look on the Lord ſingly, that the ſoul may be preſerved out of all ſin and evil, which is contrary to his pure nature in the ground and root.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64257:8"/>
            <p>But 'tis ſaid, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6. Is there any evil in the City, and the Lord hath not done it? Whence ye conclude, all evil in thought, word, and deed which appears in Men, or to the view of the World, are of the Lords own doing, and ſo good. That Scripture is not rightly tranſlated out of the Hebrew tongue; for there it is, Is there any evil in the City, and ſhall not the Lord do ſomewhat? And, in the old tranſlation it is, Cometh any Plague in a City without it be the Lords doing? So that this makes quite againſt you: For ſhall any evil or ſin be committed, and the Lord (who is pure, and holy, and juſt) not do ſomething in puniſhing or plaguing thereof; for he, in the ſecond verſe of the ſame Chapter, had ſaid to <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the Prophet; Ye onely have I known of all the Families of the Earth: Therefore I will puniſh you for all your iniquities; and he ſaith in the ſeventh verſe, Surely the Lord will do nothing, but He revealeth His ſecret to his Servants the Prophets. So that he ſpeaketh here of doing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or ſcourging the <hi>Iſralites</hi> for their ſin which he revealed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand to his Prophets, that they might declare it to the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours; ſo that the ſin and evil is from the evil nature in man, but the puniſhment thereof is from the righteous God: which puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be it either Spiritual or Corporal, is an evil indeed to him that is puniſhed, becauſe it plagues him for his iniquity; but in God it is good, becauſe it is juſtly inflicted by him upon the unrighteous Doer. But had ye Libertines kept your firſt integrity, and out of your own humane thoughts, all which are but vain, ye would never thus have run to the letter for counſel, but would have kept to God's witneſſe in your ſelves, which reproveth for all ſin and evil, which is more to us than a thouſand witneſſes from without, and which brings to a right underſtanding of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>But ye raiſe another great ſtumbling block from <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 45. where 'tis ſaid, I forme the Light and create darkneſſe, I make Peace and create Evill: I the Lord do all theſe things. Whence ye gather, that darkneſſe, and Evill which is the fruit of darkneſſe, is created by the Lord, and done by him: and therefore ye ſay, That which we count darkneſſe, and the works of darkneſſe, is as good as that which we count Light, and the works of Light. Conſider, in the wiſdom and fear of God, what the Prophet ſpeaketh of, and to what end:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64257:9"/>He ſpeaketh of <hi>Cyrus</hi> whom the Lord would raiſe up to be an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of delivering his people out of the Captivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> whom he had ſirnamed, and girded by his power for that purpoſe: which was a great Work, whereby the Nations from Eaſt to Weſt (who all had the Jewiſh People in their evil Eye) ſhould know that he was the Lord, and that there was none beſides him, that could put it into the heart of ſuch a proud Heathen as <hi>Cyrus</hi> was, to let his People go free: So, the more to illuſtrate his own Power, He moved his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to utter thoſe words above mentioned, concerning the things of the Creation, and the management thereof; He forms the Light by his natural Sun which He hath created, and the Darkneſſe or Night by the withdrawing of the Sun; He maketh peace in the Earth by reſtrayning the Oppreſſors cruelty, and inclining his heart to pitry towards the Oppreſſed, (as in this caſe of <hi>Cyrus</hi> towards the poor Jews); and createth evil or trouble, by juſtly and wiſely letting looſe the ungodly to ſcourge others for their iniquity, and to try his Peoples patience; but that the Lord who is ſimply, and perfectly Pure and Holy, who can behold no iniquity, ſhould be the Author or Creator of Spirituall evil or ſin in the Root, both the Prophet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> and Chriſt the true Light doth expreſly contradict; for one ſaith, <hi>Lamentations</hi> 3. <hi>verſe</hi> 38. <hi>Out of the mouth of the most High proceedeth not evil and good;</hi> Now by the word or mouth of the moſt High were all things made that were made, but out of the Lords mouth, or from the Lords word, proceedeth not evil and good; therefore ſin and evil in the Root, Ground, and motion were never created by him; but aroſe from ſelf, which is a ſwerving from the word by whom all things were made: the other ſaith, Every Plant that my Heavenly Father hath not planted, ſhall be plucked up: So he plainely affirmeth, there are ſome plants and motions in mans heart which the Heavenly Father never planted, and therefore will He by his powerful and good word pluck them up; whereas ye plead for their ſtanding, becauſe ye ſay, God planted them: ſo do ye directly oppoſe the true Prophet, and give him that called himſelf the Truth, the lye: Now indeed the Lord doth make Darkneſſe his ſecret place, and his pavillion round about, becauſe he dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth onely in the Light, and ſo no darkneſſe can come into his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and therefore alſo are darkneſſe and Light both a like to him: for He dwelling wholly in the Light, comprehendeth all the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64257:9"/>darkneſſe and dark waies of men, knowing nothing but Light in himſelf; but in man, as he is under a Law, which is his Light, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; its wayes are not alike to him; for he reproveth the one by the other: And therefore ought not man to apprehend them to be both alike in himſelf, but contrary; for if he doth, he believeth a Lye, and ſo deceiveth his own Soul. Therefore ceaſe from your own wiſdom, reaſonings, and diſputings, and in ſilence and humility come to the Armour of Light, which is the true ſpiritual weapon; which caſts down all reaſonings that exalt themſelves againſt the Knowledge of Chriſt, as <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, whoſe words I do alſo experimentally witneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now a word to you, more ignorant <hi>Ranters,</hi> who never taſted of the good word of God: ſome of whom perhaps ſcarce ever knew what an hours ſenſe of guilt of ſin meant in all your lives; although ye have not, at ſome time or other, been without a Checker and Reprover: who have now leightly and inconſiderately leapt into a carnal and fleſhly liberty, (which ye were in before) as it were by authority; juſtifying your evill deeds, and idle, and naughty words, and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, vain, and wandring thoughts, by taking up words, and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of others; ſaying, All is good, and therefore what ſhould we be troubled for? Alas for you poor Creatures! ye know neither the beginning, nor the end, of the work of God, even his great and ſtrange work, in turning the Creature from darkneſſe unto light, and from Satan's power unto God's power; for in Satan's power are ye at preſent held, and led Captive at his Will; ſo that unleſſe ye turn to the witneſſe of God in your conſciences, (and that while 'tis cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to day,) ye will dance into the eternal pit of everlaſting deſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion; for to the light muſt ye all come, even to Chriſt the true light, which muſt ſhew you what Veſſels of wrath ye are, as ye ſtand in the diſobedient nature, through the Fall, that ſo, your hearts being ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by that which makes manifeſt all Sin and Evill, in thought, word, and deed, Judgment may be ſet up in the earthly part; the which, as ye ſhall come humbly and ſincerely to lay down under it, ſhall be brought forth to Victory; and then ye ſhall feel Mercy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing over Judgment, and ſo the glad tidings of Salvation will be felt by you, which as ye hold faſt by Faith which purifieth the heart, fruits of righteouſneſſe, purity, chaſtity, ſobriety, temperance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will appear viſibly in you, and ſo the good Tree will be known by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64257:10"/>its fruit: Whereas now ye are fruitleſſe Trees that cumber God's earth, yea, burden and eorrupt it exceedingly; and ſo, while the Saints who ſollow Chriſt in the Croſſe to their own Wills, and, in his regeneration, feel the ſweet effects of righteouſneſſe in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs, which is peace and aſſurance for ever; ye are as a barren heath in the wilderneſſe, and know not when any true good cometh: therefore repent and turn to the Lord, with faſting, weeping, and mourning; faſting from the leaven of deceit and Hypocriſy, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for your ſins and looſneſſe, whereby God is diſhonoured, and his good Spirit grieved within you, and mourning for your killing of the juſt &amp; crucifying the Lord of life afreſh, that ſo the pure Oyl of joy and gladneſſe ye may come to feel, the leaſt drop whereof farr exceeds all your carnal pleaſnres and delights, which will quickly have an end, and be as if they had never been, and then will the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance thereof be bitter unto you: for, Are not all ſuch things bitterneſſe in the latter end? Hear what Wiſdom ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5. <hi>Hear me now therefore, Oh ye Children, and depart not from the words of my mouth: Remove thy way far from her, (to wit, the deceitfull har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, within or without, with all her inticements) and come not nigh the door of her Houſe; leſt thou give thine honour unto others, and thy years unto the cruell; leſt strangers be filled with thy wealth, and thy labours be in the houſe of a ſtranger: And thou mourn at the laſt when thy fleſh and body are conſumed, and ſay, How have I hated Inſtruction, and my heart deſpiſed reproof, and have not obeyed the voice of my Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, nor inclined mine ear to them that inſtructed me? I was almoſt in all evill, in the midſt of the Congregation and Aſſembly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for you <hi>Ranters</hi> in practiſe and principles, who are turned National Prieſts in outward ſhew, for a livelihoods ſake, though ye ſcarce or not at all regard any truth of God, or the Scriptures, which ye diſſemble by, or the People's good to whom ye ſpeak: Know, that this is the word of the Lord God unto you; that by ſuch deceit and diſſimulation (which ye count your liberty) ye treaſure up wrath to your ſelves againſt the day of wrath, and revelation of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgment of God, who (think you what ye will) will reward every man according to his works; even the Lord God, who is moſt perfectly pure, who hath his pure witneſſe in every one of you, (though at preſent ye ſtifle it for ſelf-ends) which hateth and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all diſſembling falſehood; which is for a man (under any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64257:10"/>whatſoever) to appear to be that outwardly to others (and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in a Prieſtly garbe, which bears a ſhew of external holineſſe, more then ordinary) which he is not in his mind and heart; for it is Hypocriſy, againſt which Chriſt, the true Light, hath pronounced the greater damnation: For the body is to be preſented an accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sacrifice to the Lord, which is but ones reaſonable ſervice; for it is but reaſon that it ſhould be ſo: but your bodies and Spirits are (by this means) divided and ſeperated, which ſhould go both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all actions: For ſometimes, when ye are at your hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call devotions, or in the Pulpit in a Steeple-houſe, or preaching elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, your hearts are far off; it may be, to go into ſome Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, or ranting and looſe Company, or to commit ſome unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or the like; and when ye come into ſuch company, it may be, be ready to laugh at your own Prayers and Preachings, and how ye gull the People, who know not of what ſpirit and converſation ye are: Oh ye deceitfull ones! I teſtify againſt you in the name of the Lord, That ye are the worſt of all men living in the Nations, worſe than the multitude of Prieſts, who do much that they do from a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Underſtanding and Vail that is over them; but ye tranſgreſs againſt the Light, which (I believe) ſometimes pleads with you, though ye put it from you, and would eſteem it but an imagination. Aſſure your ſelves that all you get from the People in this way of deceit, be it leſſe or more, will prove bitter morſels to you in the end, when God's witneſſe ſhall ariſe: Wherefore repent ye alſo, and turn to his witneſs, which will lead you out of all the ſnares of ſin &amp; deceit (if you will hearken to it &amp; obey it) into the pure liberty of the Sons of God, whoſe freedom ſtands not in doing what Self liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but in that which croſſeth the carnal, and leads into the paths of all Righteouſneſſe; out of which paths (I teſtify) ye are at preſent, and are in the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> who loved the wages of Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and his reward ſhall ye receive, except ye repent.</p>
            <p>And as for all you that have run out into the looſneſſe and carnall Liberty, whom God hath been pleaſed to recollect; ſo that ſome are brought, and ſome bringing, into the fold of Righteouſneſſe, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, and Peace, by believing and following the true Light: I, in the love and fear of the Lord God, exhort you to liſten continually to the voice of the good Shepherd, whoſe rod and ſtaff hath repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and comforted, and is reproving and comforting you; that ſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64257:11"/>neither ye, nor I my ſelf, may ever any more turn aſide to folly, on ſuffer a deceived Underſtanding to turn us aſide from his living truth and witneſſe, whereby we ſhould again let go the Anchor of the Soul, which is Chriſt, the hope and eternal reward to all thoſe that obey and love him, and his pure appearance, more and more, leſt the latter end be worſe then the beginning.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
